So, this isn't the type of video I'd
normally make, but when the very
foundation of what I do is attacked by
some of the most powerful people in the
world, I kind of feel like I should talk
about it. So, Trump has been up to an
awful lot ever since being elected. You
may have heard about a thing or 10 that
he's done, but I'm not here to talk
about the ramifications he's having on
the entire world, just the ramifications
he's having on one particular world,
my world, the world of science. Right
now, researchers across the United
States have been hit by several
executive orders, legal or otherwise,
including layoffs at NASA, the National
Science Foundation, and the NIH, the
National Institute of Health. In case
you don't know, the NIH provides funding
for research, research placements,
scholarships, and much more. This helps
researchers and graduate students get
the funding required to conduct
research, learn how to research, and pay
rent, among other things. So, basically,
he's cut national funding for research
across the board. Trump also barred NASA
scientists from attending the most
recent UN climate change conference
because he wants to deny climate change,
and he mischaracterized an experiment
about transgenic mice into an experiment
about turning mice transgender.
Obviously, all of this is terrible. On a
macro scale, he is trying to spread
misinformation in order to control the
people and make them think science is
useless, which will result in damage to
our planet, both socially and
ecologically. Uh but I'm actually not
here to get into that stuff. I wanted to
talk about this in a much more personal
perspective. As a bit of background, I
consider myself a scientist. I double
majored in biology and psychology. I've
made tons of science videos on this
channel, and I am a researcher. Well,
I'm trying to be a researcher. See, I'm
starting my PhD this year, which means
for the past year, I've been applying to
different graduate schools. This is a
long, drawn-out process involving
looking into programs and supervisors at
multiple schools, preparing a bunch of
information and necessary documents,
realizing that my information and
documents were not up to date and that I
have to update them, uh filling in
numerous applications that are super
long for no reason, getting on my hands
and knees to beg for reference letters,
and then sitting around and waiting for
the very real chance that all of that
was for nothing. Oh, and also, every
application costs $100 just because.
Then, what happened for me was I got
accepted into one school, but I was
waiting for a response from another
school that I wanted to go to slightly
more, but the deadline that the first
school gave me to accept their offer was
earlier than the second school ever
responded, and so I had to beg for an
extension from this school, and then beg
update from this school several times.
It was a mess. It was a stress. I'm very
glad it's over, and very fortunate to
have been accepted. So, you can imagine
if the school that I was planning on
attending now were to email me telling
me that they've rescinded my application
because of funding cuts from the
government, that would probably be my
worst nightmare. And yeah, people in the
US are currently living in my nightmare.
Here's a letter that was sent out to
applicants at Duke University last week.
Due to the recent unforeseen challenges
presented by the loss of funding for
biomedical and academic research, Duke
University faces significant
difficulties in securing external
funding to support doctoral research
opportunities, including in the areas of
research that you plan to study. Without
that external funding, Duke will not
have those same research opportunities
available. We therefore sincerely regret
to inform you that we must rescind your
offer of admission for the fall 2025
term. Here's an email from the
University of Wisconsin basically saying
the same thing. And here's a letter from
UMass Biomedical uh rescinding every
single offer. So, I guess that's just an
entire program and career path just gone
now. You can find dozens of posts on the
grad admissions subreddit right now of
people being rejected or losing their
acceptance because of their programs
having funding cut by the Trump
administration's recent actions. Uh you
can also find that many international
graduate students are being detained by
ICE for um speaking up about human
rights or just being wrongly detained
for racism reasons, which is awesome.
It's absolutely heart-wrenching and so
unfair to some of the brightest minds in
the world to have to be going through
this. After all their hard work
preparing applications, which also
involves work and school and
volunteering for the past several years,
it all gets ruined like that. And now,
so many people need to figure out what
they're going to do for the next year,
like to survive, because a lot of
graduate programs help pay for your
living expenses, and on top of that,
they'll have to reapply to places next
year, probably outside of the country
this time. Did they also just lose the
hundreds of dollars they spent on
application fees? I hope everyone got
refunds, but I honestly doubt that. I
keep thinking, like, what if this were
me? What what would I even do? I would
cry, I guess. Now, I am Canadian,
which means this has a much lower chance
of affecting me than my American
colleagues, but the threat of this is
still felt. For one, now this is a
precedent that has been set. With
Canada's federal election coming up in
just a few weeks, I'm scared because it
feels like anything can just happen now
when a new leader of the country is
elected. Not to mention that Trump is
currently threatening to forcefully
absorb my country, uh which means all of
these issues are right on my doorstep,
which is terrifying. But most
pertinently, research is an
international collaboration. America has
provided jobs for tons of international
researchers. American researchers do
studies together with others outside of
their country all the time, and a bunch
of research conferences are held there.
I even almost applied to graduate
programs in the US, and I'm very
grateful that I decided not to. Also,
for as long as I've been alive, the US
has been the world leader in
high-quality scientific publications,
publications that I read, try to learn
from, and then expand upon. With all of
that out the window, the progress of
science internationally will take a hit,
and in turn, the progress of humanity as
a whole will be slowed. And this will
result in a world-wide decline in
scientific understanding. As if the
misinformation and anti-science rhetoric
on TikTok and Twitter wasn't enough. The
ramifications of all of this are severe.
Trump wants to silence science in order
to selectively spout misinformation to
get what he wants. And what he wants in
this regard is actively harmful to the
people, to science understanding, and to
the world. On top of this all, Trump has
recently cut back on the Department of
Education, so kids in public elementary
and high schools are going to have much
less support. His whole argument is that
the US spends the most in the world on
education only to have lackluster
academic scores compared to other
countries, so he just thinks the whole
thing is a waste of money. But the
countries like Denmark and China that
he's comparing them to have radically
different educational systems and
educational philosophies. If you want to
improve academic scores, you have to
reform the system, not shut it off.
Reallocate the funds for developing a
better system instead of reallocating
them to go build nuclear warheads or go
golfing or whatever. So, it looks like
it's not just higher education getting
the boot, but education as a whole. And
it's genuinely so infuriating to see all
of this happen, but it's happening.
So, what can we do about this? Well, to
be honest, I'm not entirely sure if
anything can be done, but the first step
would be to stay aware. I'm going to
link a nice resource called the
Silencing Science Tracker, which comes
straight from Trump's arch-nemesis,
Columbia University. It's a
comprehensive list of anti-science
government policies intended to restrict
or prohibit research, education, and
discussion of scientific information
ever since Trump's first administration.
The next, I guess, would be to spread
the word. With all the chaos it's easy
to overlook the war on science because
it's not really one of the spotlighted
issues most of the time. Also, the
general population isn't going to notice
the immediate effects of this like they
will with tariffs and stuff, but this
will result in long-term rippling
consequences that I think more people
need to be aware of. There have been a
few initiatives like Stand Up for
Science, which held a protest in DC to
speak up about all this. Bill Nye was
there, which is cool, but honestly, I
feel like no one even heard about this.
I also don't really know how effective
protests are anymore. I don't know how
safe they are to do anymore. And I'm not
fully convinced that all of this madness
that I've been ranting about for the
past uh 10 minutes isn't what people
want. I mean, this is what people voted
for. And this is what people didn't show
up to vote against. And I already know
in a few weeks, when our federal
election happens, we're going to have a
voter turnout problem as well. Though,
maybe this time, with everything going
on, it'll be different. We'll see.
Science is the cornerstone to human
progress and innovation. It has nothing
to do with where you fall on a political
spectrum because it's so much more
fundamental and universal than that. It
should be above petty politics and
megalomania and corporate greed. I want
to end with an excerpt from Carl Sagan.
This was 30 years ago. We've arranged a
society on science and technology in
which nobody understands anything about
science and technology, and this
combustible mixture of ignorance and
power sooner or later is going to blow
up in our faces. I mean, who is running
the science and technology in a
democracy if the people don't know
anything about it? Science is more than
a body of knowledge. It's a way of
thinking. If we are not able to ask
skeptical questions, to interrogate
those who tell us something is true, to
be skeptical of those in authority, then
we're up for grabs for the next
charlatan politician or religious leader
who comes ambling along. It's a thing
that Jefferson laid great stress on. It
wasn't enough, he said, to enshrine some
rights in the Constitution and Bill of
Rights. The people had to be educated,
and they have to practice their
skepticism and their education.
Otherwise, we don't run the government,
the government runs us. So, yeah. Um
anyways, that's it. Sorry if I came off
a little preachy or if the fact that I'm
Canadian talking about all this rubs you
the wrong way. I've just seen so many
people in the same field and life stage
as me have their lives ruined these past
few months. So, uh I normally make deep
dives into topics in evolution and
ecology. So, if you want to check that
out, feel free. And if you have similar
feelings towards all this as I do, or
have been personally affected here,
please leave a comment. I would love to
hear your thoughts and experience. And
if you disagree with anything I said, I
would love to hear why as well. Science
is about hearing out all the sides, not
silencing the ones you don't like. Okay,
have a good day everyone. Good luck.